{
  "reference_number": "4461",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "As a food producer in NZ, the option to choose the \"two baskets\" seems attractive, as being more attainable. This should perhaps be\n used as an interim target, even for 2040. However, 30 years is a long time. I personally back Kiwis and especially food and fibre\n producing Kiwis, to come up with the technology and solutions to reach a more audacious goal over a 30 year period. I also think the\n\n brand advantage for NZ is now, in setting the bigger goal simply as it is the right thing to do."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We should keep it \"in house\" in order to both show the world it can be done, and also to make sure that we can impact as much as\n our small nation can on reducing climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "30 years is a long time in the life of technology and scientific understanding of this issue, and the related issues that arise. It would\n\n not be wise for subsequent governments to alter it because voters ask for it. but there might be circumstances where the target\n becomes meaningless as our understanding of the issues changes."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It would be good for the Government to set out plans, however they will not be able to plan for every aspect of this across all\n\nindustries. The Government will need to focus on providing long term stability for this purpose to allow industries and individuals to\ninvest in technology and R&D with confidence."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Given the widely publicised data around the percentage of New Zealand's emissions that sit in the food and fibre producers' hands,\n\nthe Government should work with stakeholders from this sector. They also need to make sure that this sector has representation\nwith the Climate Change Commission. Could the new Primary Sector council appoint a working group to liaise with the CCC on issues\n\nspecific to agriculture? The Government needs to be clear with and talking with rural lending and financial institutions about the\nstability of purpose and allow them to lend money to farmers who are undertaking development or land use changes in response to\nthis legislation. The Government needs to work with local regional and district councils whose rural rate payers will be massively\n\nimpacted to ask them what support they will need. There are also some key related issues to consider in the rural communities when\nthe Government considers the impact of this legislation. Farmers and rural businesses will be willing to invest and adapt, so how can\n\nthe Government support them? Improved electricity infrastructure and connectivity in rural communities must be a priority to allow the\nuptake of technology and to allow R&D to happen in the paddocks and regional centres where this innovation will almost certainly\n\ncome from. The electric vehicle uptake for rural people is currently limited by the range of the vehicles and the availability of charging\nstations in rural locations. This is the kind of infrastructure that the Government could lead. Government will need to consider how it\ncan be agile and responsive to rural communities' shifting needs. If land use changes occur, how can the Government rapidly support\n\nshifting rural populations with schools, roads, and access to medical care? If the rate of change is rapid or sudden, how the\nGovernment support the farmers coping with change in their mental health? Can the Government offer support for farmers financially\n\nif a piece of game changing technology becomes available and needs to be, for example, installed on 11,000 dairy farms across the\ncountry to reduce their emissions? This might be grants or low interest loans to fund emissions reducing technology or land use\n\nchanges development costs. Can the Government fund industry bodies to disseminate information about practical ways that their\nmembers can reduce their emissions?"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The desirability of the expertise is paramount. For the Climate Change Commission to have credibility, it will need to be made up of\nexperts, with cross-industry and scientific knowledge specific to the mission."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "As the need arises, subsequent governments can address this."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Information sharing will be crucial to success. It will be peer pressure organisations to act and adapt when some organisations share\n\ntheir plans and results. It will also provide collaborative and inspirational content for organisations struggling to adapt - a blueprint for\nhow others have handled it."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Food and fibre producers in NZ are concerned at a fundamental level with Kaitiakitanga and Legacy. They will want to adopt and adapt\nto this legislation. The Government needs to consider how they can best support farmers to make the required changes, without\n\npushing their costs of production up so much that their customers start buying from higher emitting competitors. There is no point in\nputting a sector out of business that is globally an emissions efficient system. The goal should be to support greater levels of\nemissions efficiencies in that system. I would also like to highlight the Government's need to prioritise training and capability for\n\npeople - we will need scientists and technology developers, but we might also need different primary sector skills or retraining\nfarmers if we end up with land use changes. Finally, I want to exhort the Government to consider this legislation alongside the full\n\ngambit of environmental issues facing food and fibre producers and on which they have worked hard already. There is no gain if we\nsacrifice water quality work or biodiversity in order to reduce emissions. Policy to reduce emissions should ensure it does not have\n\nadverse environmental outcomes in other aspects. Equally, BIOSECURITY needs to be kept front of mind when adopting or\nembracing technology for emissions reductions, especially from off-shore."
    }
  ]
}
